do
[Music]
hello good evening good day everybody
and welcome to the 98th live episode of
the ask a video show
today is a q a session as you know so
let's see who all is here with us i can
see shubhangi aryan amita
arjun abhishek alok vaibhav dhruvit
nitish twilight smart money
rtk radha binayak
samir
uttam shubang lavish
sudhir keshev tanushri
amar devosman
and lots of other people
good evening good day to all of you
thank you for being here so let's get
right into it as always let's begin so
as always i've got so many questions and
i've picked a bunch of these and let's
see how many i can answer today
so let us get into it with question
number one
this is by kedar
what are your views on dr s jayshankar's
statement that india buys less oil in a
month than europe buys in an afternoon
he also said that we are worried about
human rights issues in the us is india
enjoying the best diplomatic position
currently
in the history of the past 71 years
uh
yeah so dr s jay shankar made a very
factual statement when he was being i
think when he was being questioned by
journalists about india buying russian
oil
so that's what he said that we buy less
oil in a month from russia then europe
buys in an afternoon and i think it's a
very factual statement
it's the best possible response to these
annoying
and condescending questions that
american journalists are
quite want to ask you know
so it's a factual thing that is there
and it's absolutely correct he also said
that india is worried about human rights
about the human rights situation in the
u.s
while the americans have had this long
tradition of lecturing india
about the democracy and human rights and
such like when the fact is that the
human rights situation
in the u.s is also very concerning you
have these
shootings
school shootings mass shootings terrible
terrible things that happen routinely in
the u.s it's a routine thing in the u.s
it happens almost every every day every
other day i mean if you look at the
statistics of gun violence in the u.s
it's terrifying
right and you also have these issues of
racial profiling of of people of indian
origin being targeted recently a couple
of sikh
gentlemen were beaten up or something
like that happened very recently just
like uh just a day or two before s j
shankar dr jashankar was there in the us
maybe when it when he was there i'm not
sure
exactly what the
chronology is but yeah that happened
very recently
and you have the appalling situation
that the native americans are enduring
they've been enduring for for decades
for centuries and when it comes to the
plight of the african-american people
the black people we know it's very well
documented how terrible it is and that's
why the entire black black lives
matter
movement emerged
so that's why it emerged you know the
racial profiling that the american cops
do
if you are black you are way more
you have a much higher likelihood of
being shot for no reason by an american
cop and so on
that situation persists even today
so the human rights situation in the us
is indeed very worrying and why should
india not express concern about that
when the us
has this tendency of unnecessarily
poking into our internal affairs
so
for the first time like you're saying in
71 years or whatever whatever the time
time period is for the first time india
is talking to the u.s
in this manner
it's giving back as good it is it gets
so it's a very good development i can
see very good
assertive
language that is being used thus far it
is words but it has to be backed up by
action so i'm not saying that we need to
take certain actions about u.s human
rights or whatever but india needs to uh
be more assertive geopolitically in its
own region first of all so you need to
back up words with actions it's
words
if they are taken alone they just they
just empty words they just empty bravado
i'm not saying that's what we're doing i
think we are being very assertive right
now geopolitically in the indian ocean
region
so we are witnessing a very different
india now india is changing india is way
more confident this current government
has probably the best foreign policy i
have ever seen in the past 70 years
we are looking after our own national
interests
for a change for the first time in
forever
so yes india is doing well india's
diplomacy is pretty robust right now we
i would like to see the indian
diplomatic core being expanded beyond
the current numbers because we need many
more diplomats to engage effectively
with the world
i mean we need a diplomatic code that is
that is commensurate with this size and
cloud that india
should have i mean the size that india
has
so uh
these developments are very welcome very
positive very good for india and it
needs to continue
shankarjit says greetings from
washington dc greetings sir
uh does putin's long-term objective seem
to be capturing the whole of ukraine and
extending the russian borders to the
carpathian mountains so that russia
doesn't spend a lot on securing its
current long borders on the flat land
uh we're not quite sure what the overall
long-term objectives of mr putin are
obviously he
desires to secure russia's national
interest he is certainly concerned about
the never-ending eastward expansion of
nato and american influence and clearly
ukraine was a red line
so what he has done is is that he has
made ukraine more or less off limits for
nato the nato
[Music]
influence is there of course
they are pushing in arms and ammunition
that's what we hear
uh anti-tank missiles and spies
javelin missiles stinger missiles and so
on so they are fermenting an insurgency
in ukraine
which could go on for some time
so we don't quite know what the long
term objectives are it looks like the
russians have withdrawn for now from
kiev
and all and all that so it looks like
the uh
like the it looks like the russian
advance on kiev
was most likely a diversion for what it
was doing in
eastern ukraine and the donbass region
maybe the objective is to completely
secure donbass and get rid of the azov
uh neo-nazi elements
uh to properly denazify ukraine perhaps
maybe that's the
objective and clearly ukraine is now no
longer going to be to a significant
extent under western influence
so ukraine essentially has become a
no-go territory for the west
uh
so we still not quite sure what the
objectives are i mean the russian
military has the firepower and the
capability to take over the country of
ukraine in a matter of 48 hours they
have they have not even used the air
force and they have not even tried to
take over large parts of the interiors
of central ukraine western ukraine etc
so as of today it looks like
there is a limited objective maybe it is
uh
the donbass region eastern ukraine the
uh the coastal regions of ukraine that
about the black sea so maybe that's the
objective we still this is still a work
in progress it is it is an evolving
situation so it's it's been quite
difficult to predict the moves that mr
putin is going to make that the russian
military is going to make
initially it looked like maybe he's not
going to invade ukraine then he made he
did the invasion it looked like they're
going to take over the country in 48
hours that's how powerful the military
is and then it's dragged on for a very
long time
there has been
there have been all these conflicting
reports but we know exactly where
the russian military has has a lot of
control so maybe right now it looks like
the objective is to control
the eastern part of ukraine so let's
let's take a look at the map so that uh
you know we are clear about what we're
talking
so this here is ukraine
and the donbass region is luhansk
donetsk etc that's the eastern region of
ukraine there is kharkiv it said also
which is in the east
and then there's the coastal regions of
ukraine so the crimea peninsula has
already been taken over by russia in
a few years ago
and then you have the coastal cities of
mario paul
and odessa herson is also near the
coastal so maybe they're gonna
eventually take over these regions
because that is very
that's prime real estate especially
maritime real estate it gives them a
great deal of control over the black sea
region
so it's still
an evolving situation and let's see how
it goes right now we're not quite sure
we can tell i can say at the big picture
level that he intends to secure the
long-term
uh
national interest of russia but how
exactly is going to go about doing that
we're not quite sure as of today
says
uh
how likely is it that russia will attack
or invade finland or sweden in a
similar manner keeping in mind the
recent developments of these two
countries inching towards nato
uh
i believe see it's it's very it's very
dangerous it's foolhardy to make
predictions
in geopolitics because we never know
what's going on in the in in a leader's
mind right i mean the secret of power is
to never let let anyone know what's
really going on in your mind what you're
really thinking
so that is one of the
secrets of power so and mr putin is
really good it is
he's a past master at these games
so we're not quite sure what he intends
to do now i would say
that at present it would not be a very
good very good idea for mr putin to go
and start invading finland and
sweden
when even ukraine is not
is not completely secured right now so
let's again go to the map and and
and see where where these regions are so
so where is russia russia is over here
as you can see moscow if you can see my
mouse pointer that's moscow
the this is the western border of ma of
of russia
so where's finland finland is this big
country here in the nordic regions
which borders russia for sure
and then you have sweden which doesn't
have
a common border with russia
unless you
factor in this enclave of kaliningrad
so sweden doesn't quite have a border
with russia finland does so it would not
be very difficult for the russians to
invade
to launch an invasion of finland but the
finland is
the the people of finland the government
is quite well prepared for such an
eventuality
uh they are able to i mean i mean
they can mobilize the entire adult male
population maybe even women may be
involved in this and they have
been preparing for such an eventuality
for for decades so it may not be as easy
uh as easy as it is to see to speak
about it but it is certainly something
they could do but is it something that's
advisable
i mean if you start invading multiple
countries it's going to lead to a domino
effect it's going to lead to a
significant escalation nato may may get
involved at this point if you start
invading finland and sweden
uh
so it may not be the best thing you know
it may lead to a
first world war second world war kind of
situation
so maybe it is not the most advisable
thing to do yeah it is true that finland
is inching towards nato sweden is also
inching towards nato they are both
expressing their desire to maybe join
nato in the very near future that
possibility is right now very much on
the table
the thing is
maybe finland and sweden are not that
much of a problem for russia ukraine is
a
territory that
was historically part of russia it was
also part of the ussr and that was most
likely a red line that mr putin could
not allow the
the americans to to cross
maybe finland and sweden
he may not look at them in that manner
but it still remains to be seen so i
think
i'm i'm i believe it's a little unlikely
right now
for
a sweden or finland invasion to happen
as long as ukraine is not yet fully
secure so
most likely it's it's most probably it's
unlikely that it will happen anytime
soon
swarup says it's for the first time that
china has claimed
troop disengagement in the hot springs
region in eastern ladakh it's not clear
why china has claimed that the
disengagement has been completed
numerous rounds of diplomatic and
military talks but india and china have
been unable to end the nearly 22-month
standoff
some news sources counted china's claims
saying that not all areas of contention
at the hot springs have been cleared
what would have been the reason of this
disengagement according to you what
might they be planning are we gonna see
another face-off like june 2020 or
something big is coming
so the chinese are claiming so we had
this big standoff over there 22 months
like you say most likely yeah
most likely that's how long it has taken
give or take
so uh what we have is the situation of
of this large mass of troops on both
sides
facing each other it's a standoff like
you have in those cowboy movies you know
two sides standing with guns drawn at
each other that sort of thing so that's
what's been going on it's it's a pretty
tense situation over there it's all
been triggered off by the chinese by
their actions by their provocative
actions by their trying to
encroach into indian territory so it is
the chinese who have created the
situation in the the the indian side
responded
properly by sending adequate numbers of
troops to to face the chinese and so we
have had this standoff going on for a
very long time for nearly two years
now uh the two sides are trying to
calm the tensions to uh to an extent and
to disengage to a certain extent to
reduce the number of troops so that the
situation calms down
and i'm not sure what's been agreed but
the chinese have made the claim that the
disengagement has been completed which
is clearly not true so the chinese
always have this
this is a tactic they use repeatedly but
they say that we have
uh done everything from our side we have
uh fulfilled all the terms of the
agreement but they will keep they will
they will actually not do that but
they'll make the claim that they've done
everything and then they'll put the
owners on india for continuing tensions
so there is a tactic that strategy that
the chinese have been using
for decades not only with india but
other countries the chinese cannot be
trusted
right so maybe they want to keep the
pressure on india that's that's it's not
maybe it's it's a certainty
they want to keep india under pressure
the chinese have always wanted that
that's that's the reason why they have
never agreed to demarcate the border
there have been these endless rounds of
talks and negotiations about the border
issue but they want to keep this border
issue open and simmering so that they
can keep on needling india pressurizing
india from various locations as per
their whims and desires to keep india
permanently on the back foot on the one
side they use pakistan as as a
counterweight to india or as a
destabilizing factor and on the other
hand they have this open border issue
which is still pending and that's why
they want to keep india
complete constantly under pressure
because they fear the rise of india
obviously they fear that
so uh
what may they be planning we don't know
but it is certainly possible that they
may start something else
in the coming
days weeks months it's possible
see we have to understand the bigger
picture perspective
very soon there's gonna be i mean in the
next uh
maybe
within two years most likely there's
gonna be a general election in india
a parliamentary election
and the chinese would like
to see
a weak
government come to power in india they
would not want to see
the nda government remain in power under
somebody like mr modi or somebody else
possibly i'm just i'm just guessing they
would not like a strong leader in india
mr modi is most likely the strongest
leader india has had in decades as we
can see from the geopolitical moves from
the diplomacy and all that that's going
on india has right now become the center
of diplomacy people from all over the
world diplomats world leaders coming to
india for various purposes
so india is in a very strong position
right now india is secure militarily as
well we have
uh
all the possible everything we need
right now to to be in a good position to
defend ourselves against any chinese
malified actions
so the chinese do not like this
they want india to be weak
and for india to be weak they they would
need a weak leader to be the
leader of the country the pm of the
country so they would like to see mr
modi lose the election in 2024 and maybe
some weak coalition government some
with some random local leader should
become the prime minister like we the
situation we had in the 1990s when you
had
governments that lasted three months
four months and some very weak prime
ministers were in place who
messed up the country very badly
i will not take names at this point but
we know who they are so that's the kind
of thing they want so how do you
engineer
that sort of situation where this this
government falls and a weak government
comes into power
you do that by by
trying to
by by creating a setback
for india so for instance if there is a
military confrontation and
hypothetically india doesn't do well and
they lose in india loses some territory
the chinese are able to gain some
territory which would be a humiliation
for the indian government in the indian
army then
possibly the government could lose the
next general elections and somebody else
who would come in to power and that's
what the chinese would love to see
happen right
so it is possible that they may be
planning some kind of mischief along the
border in the coming year or two years
maximum
yeah maybe something along the silly
recorder or something
so we have to be i mean i am sure the
government
factors all of these things
takes all of these things into account
they will understand these things much
better than someone like me
they have experts and all that
so uh i'm sure we are aware of this
but i'm just saying that this is
something the chinese may
be planning they may be wishing
i am not sure if it's a very good idea
for the chinese to start a 1962 like
situation with india india is far better
prepared today so the chinese could end
up losing far more than they were hoping
to gain
i mean we are very well prepared
visa with the chinese in their in their
position in tibet whatever military
uh
camps
etc they have in tibet in chinese
occupied tibet are very much visible
they are very well known
and
and we know exactly what what they have
where they where they have it in case of
austerities it would not be difficult
for us to take everything out pinpoint
from long distance ranges and and you
know inflict a much bigger
uh humiliation that china would be would
be hoping to inflict upon india but it
is something that we have to be aware of
it is something that could be in the
offing
and we have to be prepared for it we
cannot take the chinese for granted we
can never ever be complacent i'm sure we
know our our government our armed forces
they are all very capable very
professional they would know about this
but it is a possibility so yeah we may
see another face-off in the coming days
weeks months maybe a couple of years or
maybe something even bigger and i'm sure
we are adequately
more than adequately prepared for that
okay a couple of questions about
military coups arunav says what is a
military coup any chances of it ever
happening in india and chaitan says good
day can you please help us understand
what leads to a military coordination
and why governments aren't able to
prevent it can this ever happen in
stable democracies like india us canada
et cetera are these engineered by
foreign interests interesting question
what's the coupon i don't think i've
ever taken a question like this in
detail
so a coup can happen in certain
countries there are certain conditions
preconditions that need to be met for a
coup to happen there are essentially
three preconditions that need to be to
be met for a coup
to be successful in a country first of
all the social and
economic conditions of
the target country
must be such that
the political participation is confined
to a very small fraction of the
population
which means that the majority of the
people are not are disempowered they are
not politically active at most maybe
they can vote once in a while but the
actual political participation as in
governance etc is confined to a very
small
fraction of the population there is a
very small elite that controls all the
power if you have such a situation then
a country
is ripe for a coup that's only one of
the preconditions number two
your target country must be
substantially independent
substantially independent and the
influence of foreign powers foreign
actors inside its internal political
life must be relatively limited so there
is a second precondition
of a coup being likely to succeed and
thirdly your target country where you
want to do a coup it must have a
political center which means the power
must be centralized
if there are multiple centers of power
these must be structured politically not
ethnically or linguistically
right so these are three preconditions
for a coup for an internal coup
which means from for internal actors to
carry out a coup successfully so the
social and political the economic
conditions must be such that uh the
people are marginalized and there's a
very small fraction of the population
that has all the power all the benefits
does india meet this
this credit this this particular
criterion no
india is not that sort of a country
where you have this huge disparity in
power
people are
not that marginalized the economy is
getting better
if the economy is good
if it is improving that people are
usually not
discontented and there is a reasonable
amount of political partition among the
people of india right so an internal
coup
will not succeed given this
this first precondition secondly the
target state must be substantially
independent in the influence of foreign
powers foreign actors must be inside
internal politics must be relatively
limited
well does india meet this very condition
india is reasonably substantially
independent but there i would say there
is a great amount of foreign
interference in internal affairs of
india
whether you realize it or not
even in indian politics
one well there are allegations
that certain indian political parties
are funded from abroad
certain
well yeah essentially that right
there are these ngos also in india that
gay that acquire lots of funds from
abroad for various political and other
activities
so there is a problem for india
thirdly
the target state must have a political
center it must be centrally run and if
there are multiple centers of power
these must be identified these must be
structured politically not ethnically or
linguistically in india
we have a central government but we have
very strong state governments as well
they are the federal structure and these
multiple political centers are
structured ethnically and linguistically
not politically
and therefore it's impossible for a coup
to succeed in india
impossible an internal coup to succeed
in india but now we come to precondition
let's revisit precondition 2 that the
country must be substantially free of
foreign interference substantially
independent and there must be very
little foreign interference in its
internal affairs in the case of india
that is not true there is
for foreign political interference in
india's internal affairs
i mean you see certain things happening
in coordination in india coordinated
events happening across india in various
parts of india at the same time
it could be the sign of foreign
interference in indian internal affairs
it's it's just speculation but you know
there are no coincidences in in the
world
so
uh so overall if you look at all three
preconditions
then india is is not a country where a
coup can happen
because mainly of the third precondition
that there is no actual political center
in india there is a central government
but its powers are limited
state governments have substantial
powers and state governments these
political centers in the states are
structured linguistically and
ethnically i mean if you look at the
various states as different ethnicities
which is not quite true but if even if
you do it that way then you have we
certainly have linguistic divisions
right so every state is has a certain
state language so these divisions these
political divisions are structured
linguistically
and therefore we have this so therefore
this third precondition certainly cannot
be satisfied and that is one of the
major reasons this third precondition
that's one of the major reasons why
india is never going to be a country
where a coup can succeed
i mean
they're
hypothetically
possibly hypothetically there could be
attempts
but it can never succeed in a country
like india because it's such a diverse
country with so many different centers
of power which are structured
linguistically not politically
so that's the thing but there is
certainly a significant amount of
political interference of a foreign
interference in india's internal affairs
in a variety of ways in a variety of
ways there are certain things that the
indian government is unable to do right
now it is
because of foreign political
interference let's just give an example
that we spoke about just a few minutes
ago the americans keep on insisting keep
on expressing concern about human rights
in india
right isn't that foreign interference in
indian internal affairs who the hell are
they to talk about human rights in india
when their own situation is so bad
right i mean the the first principle of
the rules-based global
order is non-interference in other
countries sovereign matters but the us
com consistently and continuously
disregards this
and we know that
they they constantly interfere in the
internal affairs of other countries we
know what they did in ukraine in 2014
they carried out a political coup in
ukraine those three preconditions were
more or less
valid they were more or less met
and the coup was carried out with
external
help not internal help
so yeah so that's how it is so that's
how a coup essentially happens it's a
fascinating topic there is a book here
where is it you see this red book here
that is the handbook on how to carry out
a coup
so
uh so if you want to carry out a coup in
a country
in some some hypothetical country then
read this book
it's a manual on how to do it it's by dr
edward luther who has appeared on my
podcast in the past right
so that's what i can say in brief about
this
okay kevin says the americans and the
russians have military bases in alaska
and chukotka
respectively and both of these areas are
very close to each other so
have there been military tensions along
this part of the two nations who
controls the chukchi sea in the bering
sea
interesting question let's go to the map
here is the map where is the region in
question
so this here
is the chokchi sea and here is the
bering sea
this is alaska which currently belongs
to the us it was sold to the us by the
russians in the 19th century
and here you have the easternmost part
of russia
so as you can see these two regions are
very closely
uh very in in close proximity
geographically so let's see where uh
where these two nations meet more or
less
okay so here we are
and again it jumps somewhere else
okay so this is the region now
google
maps is misbehaving but let's make it
behave
so this here
are the diomede islands
we have the little diameter island here
and we have the large media island there
so the smaller island
is uh it is under u.s control it it's
part of the united states it's part of
the alaskan region
and the big diomede island
it belongs to
russia
so the the distance between these two
islands is about maybe two kilometers
two to two and a half kilometers maybe
so that's one region where the two
countries come face to face i mean you
can you can
stand on the beach and you can see the
other country from there
so that's one region then you have the
uh
then you have the bearing straight
whoa google earth is jumping around
so this is the bearing sea and this here
is the bearing straight
so this island here it belongs to the us
as you can see it's part of alaska
and over here
you actually have the bearing island
which gives its name to the bearing
straight
so this is
this over here you have a considerable
distance maybe a few hundred kilometers
between these two
countries over here
so in the past in the past during the
cold war there used to be these uh
patrols that the two countries would
undertake sea patrols by ships and
aerial patrols
using heavy strategic bombers
excuse me and the two uh militaries
would often come into contact the
the air forces would like routinely come
into contact and the pilots would even
wave at each other sometimes it there
would be ten situations where the planes
would come too close and they would be
aggressive flying and all that
it's even happened that ships have
collided submarines have collided that
sort of thing so the situation in the
past during the days of the ussr in the
cold war used to be often quite tense
these days also i am sure that there are
tensions but the tension the the
intensity of the tension seems to be
lesser
currently
when we talk about the diameter islands
i believe in the 1980s a u.s swimmer
actually
swam across this this uh the distance
between the two islands
and the event was welcomed by the
leadership of the both the countries
so that's the situation where we have
today that we have today who controls
the sea it's an open sea it's
international water so nobody actually
controls it but both navies would patrol
it you would have surface
naval vessels and submarines as well and
the same goes about the bering sea it is
open waters international water so
nobody officially controlled it but both
navies would have significant presences
over here especially nuclear submarines
and
such like
vessels
so that in brief is the situation in
this region very interesting uh part of
the world
rama lakshmi this is a question first of
all i would like to thank rama lakshmi
ramallah thank you for your for for
posting the
the time stamps after all of these
sessions i really appreciate it and i
would like to also thank the other
people who have posted time stamps in
the past like akash buller and harshit
and whoever else has been doing that
thank you very much all of you and
especially rama lakshmi who is doing it
currently thank you so much i really
appreciate it
so what is the question uh ten days back
i saw a tweet in which it's a detailed
video about the indo-arya aryan
migration where he speaks that
the aryan invasion theory is debunked
decades ago and he presents various
documents and genetic studies that and
he also took your video on the art
invasion he proved various statements
wrong by showing different documents he
even mentioned out of india theory is
not true completely and please
throw some clarification or make a video
could you please please look at the
video it okay
so yeah i've heard that somebody has
made some kind of of a
of a response video or rebuttal video to
the various
videos that i have on the rn invasion
myth
i haven't seen it
i don't believe that everybody needs to
be responded to
uh and i believe it's a longish video
one hour plus that's what i hear and i
believe the title of the video is about
when did sanskrit enter india or
something like that and apparently he's
trying to prove that sanskrit
entered into india at a certain date
range based on genetic evidence
so i have not seen the details but the
premise seems ridiculous to me because
you cannot link language and genetics
there is no linkage
between language culture and religion
and genetics
your genetics
cannot tell
anyone what language you speak what
religion or culture you follow
i am speaking english right now does it
mean that i have english genetics
it doesn't mean that right so there is
absolutely no connection between
language
and genetics culture and genetics
religion and genetics so just because
there is a certain amount of genetic
evidence for whatever doesn't mean that
a certain culture or religion or
language came along with it it doesn't
mean that at all
so the entire premise of basing
the entry of a language into a region
based on genetic influx is completely
baseless it's it's it's completely
incorrect now i have not seen the video
i have not seen what uh
arguments he has made i don't i don't
i've not seen what data he has presented
uh
maybe in the future i may do it i like i
said i you don't have to respond to
everybody who comes across and tries to
respond to you that is gonna essentially
drag you it's gonna make you follow
their agenda i also hear that some
people have been speaking on my behalf
and saying that i'm open to a debate i
have never said that
so uh maybe i will look into in the
future i these days i don't
watch long videos i simply don't have
the time i haven't seen a long form
podcast in years
in like a couple of years so
so i'll see i will i will consider
watching the video if if if i get the
time and maybe maybe if it is worth
responding to
then i may respond to it
so let's see how it goes i will i will
certainly take this uh as something i
can
address
maybe in the future
okay kolkata guys says i'm from varanasi
kolkata guy from varanasi all right
uh in one of your videos you were
talking about the celtic goddess danu
and her origin in india could you please
tell us a bit about that
this is a very interesting topic
very ancient connections
that originate in india
so uh i'm not sure how many of you know
it but in the rigveda
our oldest known text the oldest known
literature in humanity
so in this
lit in this text in the big veda
we have the mention of a
goddess
called dhanu
she is a primordial river goddess she's
a river goddess all right and she is the
progenitor of the dhanava clan
of ancient indians they are asuras they
are they are termed as asuras and they
are called
because they are the descendants the
children of danu
so danu is a river goddess her
descendants her children are offspring
are the dhanavas
who are asuras
and that's the story and and in the
rigveda she is the mother of the great
sea serpent vritra
is the great sea serpent who encircled
the ocean and cut off access to water to
all humanity and and
and the great warrior the great lord
indra had to fight this great sea
monster and defeat him and free the
waters of the world so that is the
mythical mythological story that we have
maybe it's it's something that
originates in some real life event that
must have happened very long ago ago and
it was
it was mythologized in that manner in
increa in the form of a sea monster and
all that but dhanu
was the mother of viritra this great sea
monster in the rigveda right and she was
the progenitor of the dhanava clan
of ancient indians of asuras
and apparently the dhanavas were kind of
kind of
a little bit slightly evil
and there was this clash this war and
they they lost the war they lost the
battle and they were forced into exile
out of india and that's where the story
ends we don't know what happened to them
what happened to these people the dhana
was
now if you look at geography it tells
you a very interesting story so let's go
back to the map
let's remove this for now
so if we look so we talk about ukraine
these days right
let's go to the city of kiev
kiev kiev cave
so this city sits on a certain river
that river is called the niper
sniper so there's a whole bunch of
rivers in eastern europe that are named
dawn
danube knight
neister
and so on and so forth
and the
linguistic origin of all of these rivers
is the word dhanu
the river goddess the ancient river
goddess
so it looks like these river names that
trace the eastward migration
of a bunch of people
who worshipped this river goddess dhanu
maybe it was the dhanavas who were
expelled out of india forced our force
into a permanent exile and they went
westwards gradually and whichever great
river they found they named it after
their ancestor the great
lady danu
right
and the uh
the word
for water in the ancient
language the saka language was dhanu
and there's a lot of
yeah so even in the i think old persian
language the the name for drop or water
was dhanu
and and certainly that's how it is
so you can see that there is this
significant influence of dhanu in
eastern europe in among the skitian
peoples among the all the indo-european
peoples
and these river names they seem to trace
the westward the gradual
westward migration of a bunch of people
who
revered
the goddess the the rigvedic goddess
dhanu
right and now we find that
if we go all the way west to the island
of ireland
if we look at their ancient foundational
story their mythological foundational
story
so the according to that founded
founding story of ireland the first
peoples of ireland
were called the people of the goddess
dhanu
the tuata didn't
that's what that that was the name and
they revere the ancient their mother
goddess who was a river goddess called
right i mean can this ever be a
coincidence
so it's clear that a bunch of people
went out of india migrated westwards out
of india
and gradually
made their way across europe from east
to west and whichever great river they
found in europe and they said they must
have settled on along these rivers for
some time they named all of these rivers
after
goddess dhanu and eventually it looks
like they ended up all the way west in
ireland
where the people of ireland considered
dhanu to be their progenitor mother
goddess the river goddess
so that is the story
of
the goddess dhanu the irish goddess
dhanu which seems clearly to be the same
as the rigvedic goddess
i'm sure there were several centuries
between the
the events that led to the
expulsion of the dhanava people from
india
and their eventual settlement all the
way west in ireland maybe that took more
than a thousand years possibly we don't
quite know i am sure if we do the right
kind of research we may be able to trace
back the chronology of the migration
possibly
but that in in a nutshell is the story
a rig vedic goddess who ends up in
ireland as the mother goddess of the
irish people isn't that fascinating
they just says how can we deduce the
cushions were indian when
cut pieces one
united five clans of the uhi
and then defeated the greeks and the
parthians and the uhr of chinese origin
i found this info in ancient india by rc
okay very good question
so like i have said i i mean i have
recommended rc majumdar in the past i've
said it's a very good source of
information about ancient india now we
have to oh i also put a caveat in there
i said that these books were written
almost a century ago and therefore they
would reflect the knowledge that was
available
at that time 100 or so years ago maybe
80 years ago that is very old knowledge
much of it is outdated the books are
very still very good reference books for
information about ancient india but we
have to always keep in mind that this
information is outdated in in some in
some cases in many cases perhaps
right
so
yeah the the the the people the kushan
the ancestors of the koshan the chinese
called them the uhi so does it mean they
were chinese
does it mean they're chinese because
today we know them by a chinese name
does it mean that they were of chinese
origin
obviously not that it's not a logical
connection
i mean the chinese can call the indians
hindu
i think the name the chinese have
currently for india is hindu and they
would have some name for the indian
people also so because there is a
chinese name for indians does it mean
that we are in we are chinese now
the the
russians
found this pit grave culture
ancient five thousand-year-old
pit graves
the graves they look like pits
and the russian name for the word
pit
is yamna
so they called these people the yamnaya
people
does it mean the yamnaya people of 5000
years ago they were russians
because they we we use a russian name to
call them to to to
for them today
no
just because we use a russian name for
that for the clan of people does it mean
they were russians and similarly if the
ancestors of the kushan kushans were
called the uhc or the chinese it doesn't
mean they were chinese it's just a
chinese name for that we don't have to
use the chinese name for that
right
so the
most likely the ancestors of the people
who were later known as the kushans most
likely they were the ancient tushar
people
and the english-speaking historians they
call them the tokarians because they
don't want to use the sanskrit word so
don't use the word tushar use the word
tokarian which obviously is
based upon the word tushar
so most likely the ancestors of the
kushan people
who let me show on the map
they most
where the where did they live they lived
in the tarim river basin region and
present day xinjiang
where is the tharium river
this is the hotan river the tarim river
is here i believe
whichever is this this is the arkan
river
all right
all right where is that where is the
desert
thorim river let's let's look for the
tharim river
yeah it's currently in china currently
where is it where is it
looks like i found it
yeah this is the tarim river
so in the tharim river basin
that's where the ancestors of the
kushans lived and they were most likely
known as the tushara people and they
were of indian origin how do we know we
find all these tarin basin mummies there
and the mummies look kind of european
you know they are like tall six feet
tall etc some of them are over six feet
tall they seem to have fair skin
many of them have red hair or blonde
hair
right so they look like they are
european
in ethnicity but when we examine the dna
of the males
they are
almost exclusively r1a1a which is an
indian origin lineage
so maybe there was some inter marriage
between
eurasian peoples and indians or
something like that which produced the
tushar people
and so on but the but the uh
ethnicity was very clearly indian the
patrilineal lineages haplogroups were
decidedly of indian origin
and
if you look at the mummies they don't
they don't look chinese at all they
don't look chinese in any way whatsoever
so this word uh which the chinese use
and which historians use nowadays for
the ancestors of the kushans it is very
misleading it is a chinese term for a
foreign people for a people that the
chinese consider to be foreigners
western barbarians
so that's what it is that you achieve
were not chinese the koshans were not
chinese they were indians i just gave
you genetic evidence you can look up you
can google the tarin base in mummies you
can see how they look they are very well
preserved their facial features are very
clearly apparent they are not chinese in
any way whatsoever one could call the
tushara people the tokarians
as
one could regard them as the easternmost
sketians
so the sketians were an indo-iranian
group they were of indian origin that is
also very well known they were also
almost exclusively of the r1 a1a lineage
the sketians and similarly for the
koshans so there you have it they were
of indian origin they would have mixed
mixed blood because they
because they traveled around and they
would have inter intermingled with
various other peoples but
overall they were of indian ethnicity
and clearly of indian culture
because when the kushans
re-entered india
after several thousand years they had no
trouble assimilating with the indian
population there was no cultural
religious strife whatsoever it was the
same culture
the same
more or less the same ethnicity
pratik says
now thank you pratik i appreciate it so
the question is
do you think the us military obsession
the new obsession with aliens is just to
give importance to the newly created
space force
and create unnecessary fear in their
congress and senate to increase the
military budget through an unseen and
unknown adversary also to boost their
war economy it's possible
so apparently aliens only
only appear in the us i mean
why hasn't india seen any
alien visitation
why don't we get videos from india about
aliens
flying over bangalore bengaluru or
chennai
or mumbai
or guwahati or impal or delhi or ladakh
why do we only see these ufos
in u.s
airspace why is that
so the americans are right now in the
last couple of years they've been
releasing very very grainy low quality
black and white videos of supposedly
alien
aircraft spacecraft
doing uh
defying the laws of physics and all that
i mean why is all of this footage so
grainy is why is it so black and white
they have the best equipment the us air
force and the americans they have the
best cameras
but they only produce black and white
green footage why is that
why is that
so it doesn't make much sense to me but
it's very interesting that they are
doing this they have created the space
force i believe it was president trump
who initiated the creation of the space
force and obviously the space force will
need a good budget a few
hundreds of billions of dollars possibly
maybe if not hundreds maybe at least 100
maybe i would imagine so they want money
so they have to create some kind of
threat right
so they uh
and
that threat should be something that the
public sees feels and
accepts only then will the public accept
a large amount of money going into the
space force otherwise it would look like
wasteful expenditure so maybe that's why
they're doing it i mean i would be
really happy if we actually find
evidence of aliens having visited us or
actively visiting us that would be great
nothing would make me happier
to see the evidence of first contact
between us and another
civilization from from another star
system maybe that would be wonderful
nothing would would make me happier than
that but thus far i unfortunately have
seen no evidence whatsoever that such a
thing
has
happened
i mean there is evidence there are
claims of ufos
in africa in zimbabwe
and some people claim that if you go to
mount kailash you see certain weird
activity lights the sky and all that
so uh
one does hear all of this but
i'm not quite sure how
how reliable how verifiable how true all
of it is some of it is intriguing for
sure but there is no
undeniable hard evidence so it's still
something that we have to keep an open
mind about but it's still
something that i'm as of now skeptical
about
pratik says life forms like like
cryptobiotic in the spores and certain
bacteria are extremely resistant and
evolve at a faster rate to adapt in
harsh situations conditions researchers
have even discovered new strains of
evolved bacteria that were carried
unintentionally to the international
space station and survived there for
years
so here's my question as spacecrafts
cannot be sterilized completely is there
a possibility that we have accidentally
contaminated mars with life during space
missions before even stepping on mars
yes absolutely
i think it's very likely that we have
sent
earth bacteria to mars and wherever else
we have sent spacecraft
it's impossible to thoroughly and 100
percent
sterilize any spacecraft it's almost
it's it's impossible
you can never
guarantee a hundred percent
sterilization of spacecraft and i'm not
sure even if that's the objective when
we do that you know when we send
spacecraft to another planet
so
i think it's a guarantee that we have
sent earth bacteria to mars and maybe
they are surviving there it's quite
possible like you said certain bacteria
are very hardy they don't die they're
very hard to kill off they can survive
in the vacuum of vacuum of space
recently an israeli spacecraft crashed
on the moon it was carrying these
tardigrades these water bears
microscopic animals which are extremely
hardy they are almost impossible to kill
so it's quite likely they must have
survived there and they
would possibly still be alive on the
surface of the moon
where the spacecraft crashed so yes
there's a very high
it's almost a guarantee that we have
contaminated wherever we have sent
spacecraft
we have sent spacecraft to the surface
of
venus
the venera landers sent by the ussr
i'm not sure if earth bacteria can
survive in that environment on venus
with the increa incredibly high
temperatures and pressures and the the
rain of sulfuric acid but maybe even
there
one could
possibly see the survival of of earth
bacteria in which case it would be an
interesting situation there right now
so uh
and we've also sent spacecraft to the
surface of titan which is a moon of
saturn
so even there there could be
contamination so wherever you send
something on the surface of a planet or
into the atmosphere of a planet there's
always a very high likelihood that
you're contaminating that place that
planet
with earth bacteria so
it's almost a guarantee that it's
already happened
rahul says why why okay number seven
you're asking
seventh attempt to ask me the question
why on earth
sardar vallabhbhai patel always escapes
criticism he went to suppress the naval
mutiny he brought the he thought that
partition can solve various problems
the way he treated swashboards was
terrible he supported gandhi and was
brutal to moses 1939 election he also
said lyon is born king not elected and
so on
why does no one criticize him plus dr
ambedkar agreed that subhash bose gave
us independence but sardar patel was all
for gandhi gandhi
interesting question why does uh wallaby
patel
escape criticism well one of the things
he did was he reunified india after the
transfer of power from the british to
the congress party
he did a great job of unifying india of
forcing
in one way or the other all of these
little princely states to accede to the
dominion today to the
dominion of india it was then a dominion
status it was not independence right so
he unified the country by hook or by
crook so that is one great um
that is there is a great debt that we
owe
to
wallaby patel and that's one of the
reasons why people are very reluctant to
criticize him in any way whatsoever
because was it not for his incredible
efforts at that time post 1947 15th
august india would be a deeply
fragmented country it would not be a
country it would be a bunch of little
kingdoms that's what the british wanted
right so that's what mr patel did and
that's that's why people are very
grateful to him for
for that work now
now you said that he went on to suppress
the naval mutiny well that is very much
true
that is very much true
so in 1946 the indian the british indian
navy rebelled against the british
the rebellion spread like a wildfire i
have made a separate video on that you
can look it up the rebellion spread like
wildfire in just a few days the entire
almost the entire indian navy
was up in arms against the british
it carried
a huge amount of fire power
right
and you had ships all the way from the
gulf of aden and the middle east
all the way to singapore all the way to
the andamans and in the indian ocean
region from vishakhapatnam to bombay to
karachi bomb it was called bombay in
those days karachi etc where you had all
the ships
that had declared against the british
only one or two ships commanders were
loyal stooges of the british everybody
else
rebelled
and soon you had riots in places like
bombay and karachi and hundreds if not
thousands of innocent civilians were
killed by the british
they opened fire they ordered the police
not the police but the army to open fire
and this is an event even possibly in
vishakapatnam we're not quite sure all
of this has been suppressed by our
historians
and
if this had spread to the indian army
the the british indian army it would
have given india independence then and
there
because the entire basis
of the british control over the indian
subcontinent was the armed forces
they controlled india through the threat
of violence
it is the armed forces that gave them
power in india
and the armed forces were comprised of
indians
right
so the indian navy rebelled
and there was even this incident of them
opening fire in mumbai in bombay from
the
harbor and the people rebelled the
people with did rioting in these cities
and very soon it could have spread to
the indian army had it spread to the
indian army it was game over for the
british and we would have had we would
have snatched independence by force
on our terms
from the british
so what mr gandhi did is he sent his
enforcer
mr patel
to bombay
to negotiate with the
with the rebellious
uh
naval soldiers the sailors
and
mr patel he assured them
that nothing no action will be taken
against you
you will not be caught marshalled you
will be given everything your salary and
everything and uh things will go back to
normal work but please surrender stop
this nonsense
and what the soldiers what the sailors
found was that the indian national
congress the congress party was against
the naval rebellion the muslim league of
jannah was against the naval rebellion
only the communists were supporting it
the communists had their own ulterior
motives for this because they wished for
a great
communist revolution in india so maybe
they could take advantage of this that's
why they were supporting the naval
rebellion
naval mutiny whatever you call it so the
congress party was against it gandhi
criticized it in very harsh terms and mr
patel was mr gandhi's right-hand man his
enforcer mr patel did the and
played the enforcer role in the congress
party
he is the guy who did all the
organizational stuff and he is the guy
who maintained discipline in the
congress party so gandhi relied on just
one person for this job it is mr patel
and mr patel was 100 loyal to mr gandhi
right
so mr patel went to bombay he quelled
the rebellion he persuaded the indian
navy to give up the rebellion
and as soon as they gave up
as they surrendered their arms and ships
and everything they were thrown into
jail
they were all court-martialed they were
imprisoned for months or years
they lost their salaries they lost their
pensions they lost everything
and no one knows afterwards what
happened to those people
it's not been recorded our historians
have made sure that these
events are mostly erased from our
history so mr patel
ensured that india did not get
independence in 1946 he ensured that
india got independence on british terms
not indian terms
which is why we had a partition had the
royal naval the indian navy mutiny
succeeded
there would have been no partition of
india
and the congress party may most likely
not have come to power
it would have been a true revolution
and a true independence on indian terms
so mr patel
ensured
that did not happen he ensured that mr
gandhi prevailed and mr nehru pate mr
nehru prevailed so so that is the role
that mr patel played it is not a very
good role
so
if you wish to criticize mr patel for
that feel free to do that
the the the facts are very clear
the facts are very clear he ensured
that the rebellion failed
and the promises he made
were immediately broken
so these are facts that no one can deny
atharva says do you think the current
system of government in which we have
ceremonial president and governors is a
waste of taxpayers money why do we need
a ceremonial president in the country or
governor is in or governors in states
either the head of state should be a
ceremonial monarch whom people know or
the head of state must possess real
powers the ceremonial president is
really a waste of money like the
rashtrapati bhavan pm modi or any other
future pm can also be the head of the
state
the president can be subjected to
parliamentary confidence we may create a
whole new title such as the supreme
minister maybe a maha mantri who is both
head of state and government
so i i agree to a large extent these
ceremonial positions are pointless
and you will see that wherever in the
world you have the ceremonial positions
it's usually something that you see in
formerly colonized countries
so when the transfer of power
all of these formerly colonized
countries they have witnessed a transfer
of power on the terms of the colonizing
force
to some dictator or to some local
political group
in india it was the
the gandhi nehru the congress party
essentially
so these people who came to power after
the transfer of power from the british
to india they were very nostalgic about
british rule they loved it so much they
loved having a head of state which was
the british king at the time
so they wish to to create a position
like that and that's why they created
this ceremonial president
who has no actual powers but he is the
title or head of state which is a
completely pointless thing why do we
need that what function does it serve
it serves no function no purpose to have
such a person
so such a such a such a role
in governance and similarly for these
governors of states who actually
can't do much
why can't the elected chief minister
have all the powers why do we need
somebody on top of him or her
so if you look at countries
that have not been colonized you will
see no such thing ever
in france the person who is elected
president is the head of state there is
nobody above him or her there is no
titular or ceremonial position in the
u.s
the president is the head of state the
president is indirectly elected by the
people indirectly
and there is no title or ceremonial
position
so why can't india
trim down on this fat and
remove all these unnecessary
ceremonial roles which are essentially a
waste of taxpayer money i i agree
nothing against the people who hold the
position of president or whatever many
of them are really good people
in the past we have had certain very
people who are not quite fit for any
such role but yeah currently of course
we have a good person
but i agree that these ceremonial
positions are pointless
siddharth says from the size of it i
feel that the capacity of the nuclear
warhead that the brahmos missile can
carry off is of a low yield tactical
size
okay you feel that waves earth very good
now what do we know about the brahmos
it can carry a warhead which is 200
kilos or 300 kilos depending on on which
brahmos variant we are talking about i
think the naval brahmos can carry a
warhead of 200 kilos
and the the land-based one or the air
based one may have about
a capacity of 300 kilos i'm not sure
which variant has which capacity but
there is a 200
kilo capacity and there's a 300 kilo
capacity
so you feel sir that the this capacity
is that of a low yield tactical nuclear
warrant size when you talk about a
tactical warhead you're talking about
maybe 10 kilo tons 20 kiloton 30
kilotons that sort of
yield explosive yield right
so that's what you say now let me put
some facts across if you look at
plutonium
see typically nowadays we don't use
uranium weapons we use plutonium weapons
or we use weapons that have uranium as
well as plutonium uranium triggers the
blast and then there's a secondary
fusion reaction that takes place in
which plutonium is fused or efficient or
whatever depending on what kind of
warhead you're using
so if you have a fission bomb
it's
it's a less efficient
bomb than than a
thermonuclear warhead which is a fission
fusion reaction a primary fission
reaction that gives rise to a secondary
fusion reaction that's a different kind
of thing
so
if you have
a fission bomb it's going to be kind of
inefficient now the hiroshima bomb which
was very heavy it gave a blast yield of
15 kilotons i believe and the nagasaki
warhead gave a yield of 21 kilotons of
tnt
right
now let's take a look at existing
thermonuclear warheads that we know
about we don't know the kind of
thermonuclear warheads we have in our
arsenal we india have in our arsenal it
has never been made public
we have thermonuclear warheads for sure
now let's take a look at a few american
thermonuclear warheads so there is the
w76 warhead whose weight is 164
kilograms
it has a blast yield of 100 kilotons
that is massive
there is not a small low yield tactical
warhead that's a strategic kind of blast
i mean strategic tactical depends on how
far you send it
but
so that's not a low yield a hundred
kilotons its weight is 164. you can
easily put it inside a brahmos
the w89 warhead of the americans it has
a weight of about 150 kilos its yield is
200 kilotons which is massive
twice that of the w76
then you have the w87 nuclear warhead
which is a thermonuclear warhead all
three of these are thermonuclear
warheads
so the w87 has a weight of 200 kilos
it has a yield of 400 kilotons of tnt
which is
massive
so all three of these warheads can
easily fit inside any brahmos missile
so that's not low yield assuming india
also has thermonuclear warheads that are
similar to these w
a
family of warheads of the us
then we would also be able to place
a high yield thermonuclear warhead
inside a brahmos missile
right
possibly which has a yield of 400 or 500
kilo tons of tnt almost half a mega mega
en of tnt if you have developed that
sort of warhead
so the brahmos is not going to carry
a low yield tactical warhead it's going
to carry a massive sub megaton
nuclear warhead most likely
there you have it
next question
sri nidhi says is it possible in india
to see private defense companies
including r d like super giants lockheed
martin general atomics within the next
eight to ten years
um
see when it comes to these massive super
giants like lockheed martin general
atomics
they are very mature organizations with
very mature technology that has been
developed over decades
so it takes time for your technology
defense manufacturing technology to
mature so for instance india is
developing all these uh
long endurance
drones
similar to the
reaper and predator drones that the
americans have we are developing our own
uh family of drones the rostam drone is
called or whatever it is
so that is the first iteration of the
technology now you take it further you
create new variants of this with higher
payloads higher
endurance higher altitude or whatever so
it takes time for this to happen it is
certainly possible to create a mature
drone manufacturing ecosystem or
artillery manufacturing ecosystem or
whatever it is in a decade or so
most likely two decades
we have drdo we have ha hal which have
been in place for decades
so they could evolve into super giants
maybe in the next 10 years if this if
sufficient funding is made available so
i believe we're going to see the
emergence of a defense manufacturing
ecosystem in india
over the next
decade
two decades
some of these firms may remain small if
they are producing some specialized
spare parts or whatever some of these
firms could become super giants in the
next 10 20 years depending on the amount
of investment the amount of funding
and whether they are like hl or drd or
something so you could see a whole range
of companies coming up i believe as of
today as of the next decade two decades
private companies may not become that
big that rapidly
but you will see the small companies and
medium-sized companies certainly
emerging over the next decade
especially in things like ship ship
manufacturing submarines and so on
some of these companies
may become quite big
but super giants will take time maybe
maybe 20 years
but it could also be accelerated
depending on how much funding is
available it all depends on the funding
we have the power we have the brains
we have the brightest brains in the
country and the technology is all well
if you have the brains and you have the
engineering expertise you can certainly
create the technology
so it is possible in the next 10 20
years eight to 10 years is a little
short
duration of time but certainly the next
20 years we may see the emergence of a
full-fledged ecosystem with all kinds of
companies private companies small ones
medium ones even large ones
so i would give it 20 years but in the
next 10 years we will certainly see the
formation of this ecosystem
okay extremis says
i wish to push back on you about
something your appraisal of the current
world's geopolitical state and the
motivations of the actors within it is
quite realist in nature you often say
that if a geopolitical entity can
increase its power then it will
and this seems to be a natural state of
awareness in your estimation of the
present geopolitical world you put it in
quite a moral terms those who can do
yes
this seems to be quite in contrast to
the way you describe the historical
world you state that india has had its
wealth stolen to the in the western
powers
are the transgressors or otherwise bad
moral actors
can we not by your currently stated
morality see this in the same light was
the loss of wealth simply a great
geopolitical failure on india's part
according to your previously stated
views on geopolitics see it's like this
when you study
geopolitics when you analyze geopolitics
when you
study the
cause and effect chain
when you study the nature of power and
the
statics and dynamics of power you have
to keep it completely immoral it has to
be cold and precise
you cannot bring in emotions
into that into that analysis into that
study
so that's how you study geopolitics you
approach it dispassionately without
bringing an emotion and without bringing
in a certain perspective a personal
perspective
that's the only way you can actually
understand and study
geopolitics and power
right so that's why i describe
the geopolitical situation etc in these
dispassionate terms those who can will
do it that's the nature of power
now when i talk about india i'm talking
from an indian perspective right
so that's how it is
i obviously am from a country that has
suffered a thousand years of all of this
invasions destruction ridiculous amounts
of destruction horrific genocide that
has never been documented it is not even
recognized today no historian speaks
about it
and so on so that is something that is
personal to all indians
so when you speak about that particular
thing there's going to be
some emotion to that
there's gonna be a personal perspective
that is not going to be the
dispassionate
cold perspective that you have when you
study geopolitics so when you when you
when you talk about the concepts and
principles of geopolitics about the
nature of power about the dynamics of
power
and all that you have to describe all of
that in very cold clinical immoral terms
but when you talk about history
and who were the transgressors who was
the
who are the oppressors who were the
victims that is going to be looked upon
differently it doesn't mean that one
perspective is wrong and one perspective
is right both perspectives are correct
what happened
is of course a geopolitical failure
there was a lack of political unity when
these
turkic invasions began and and
when the british came into india there
was for some time
political unity a single political force
in india the maratha empire
but it unfortunately
collapsed over time over a certain
period of time
so they so you can study it completely
clinically completely
clinically coldly but you can also
from your own perspective say it how it
is and there were good actors and bad
actors right
i mean see it's like this
invasions have happened throughout
history human history
but does an invasion have to lead to
cultural genocide and
population genocide is that necessary
what the british did
was that they engineered hundreds of
artificial famines they killed over 100
million indians
i mean
you can approach that coolly clinically
from one perspective that this is what
power can do yeah sure but as an indian
i'm gonna also approach
approach it as an indian
so and and when india
re-emerges the power
you may see certain action that india
will take
maybe
to redress certain things
that's what countries do let's take a
different example for instance
in the
in the 13th century was it
in the in the 12th century
we had the emergence of the mongol
empire under the great conqueror ching
is khan
now he wished to trade with the
empire to the west to the west of india
so he sent a trade delegation a bunch of
merchants the merchants were massacred
by the by the
turks who were ruling quran
and all the goods were stolen
so then chinese con sent three
ambassadors to quran to
ask for justice
so these ambassadors were humiliated one
was beheaded
and then chingish khan decided to
retaliate
so
he could have approached it clinically
coldly that this is how geopolitics
works
but he decided to take revenge and and
to protect his reputation
so there is emotion in that too
so it's it's a mix of all these factors
when you study something you have to do
it dispassionately but when you react
you can react emotionally so these are
two different concepts two different
things
shimra says can china and india ever be
friends and allies not unequal allies
like america and britain but rather to
equal and ancient civilizations standing
together in mutual respect let's
understand this mutual respect respect
depends on strength
you can have an equal relationship
between two countries two civilizations
that are equally strong
then there will be
an equal relationship
when you have a country like china whose
gdp is five times that of india
there can be never there can never be an
equal relationship
they will they will not respect india
why should they respect india why should
they respect a nation that has one fifth
of their gdp
that's not how it works
and there are no friendships in
geopolitics there are alliances
temporary alliances
and when things change the alliances may
dissolve
and america and britain are very
unequalized precisely because of this
dynamic
the british have no strength today they
are not a major geopolitical player
their gdp is tiny compared to that of
the us
it's a fraction of that of the us and
that's why the u.s bosses around britain
it the americans essentially
to put it crudely treat the british as
their as their pet poodle right that's
how they they treat the british
it's a vasal state so is australia so is
new zealand so is canada
so that is the only consideration in
geopolitics
power
your national strength your
comprehensive national power
your gdp your military the strength of
the military and other factors that is
what determines how much respect you get
that's the only thing no one cares how
culturally advanced you are and how many
libraries you have
and how many forms of classical dance
you have
and so on no one cares the only
consideration in geopolitics is hard
power
and you cannot have any soft power
unless you first have hard power right
so that is where it goes so india and
china can forget about friendship there
can be never there is no such thing as
friendship alliances can happen but when
you have two major powers with the
common border
they are typically going to be either in
an uneasy state of truth or they are
going to
have hostilities
so if india and china are to be allies
in the future someday
it will happen only if these two
civilizations don't have a shared border
which can only happen if tibet is
restored to independence
right
and i do not consider india and china to
be equal ancient civilizations
from a civilizational perspective
china is a newcomer to the
civilizational club the chinese
civilization is about three three and a
half thousand years old at most
india is the oldest known civilization
it goes way
beyond the bronze age
india's civilization has a recorded
history of at least 10 000 years if not
more
so there is no question of these two
civilizations being equal
india has exported so much culture to
china china has given india nothing back
in return it's not like we want
something but the cultural exchange has
always been one-sided
right so from a civilizational
perspective india and china are not
equal india is way greater than china
but from a geopolitical hard power
perspective currently china is five
times the size of india
from the economic strength perspective
and militarily also it has a much bigger
military look at the number of fighter
planes they have look at the number of
warships they have look at the number of
submarines they have come on
right
the only thing that
restores some sanity and balance is that
india possesses
the the ultimate weapon which is the
nuclear weapon right so uh
there is no not going to be mutual
respect unless both civilizations are on
equal terms from the perspective of hard
power only then there could be
a mutual
respect kind of situation and maybe an
alliance if tibet is is a buffer state
in between
rajoshi says do you think the james webb
telescope would really be able to make
groundbreaking discoveries which could
prove theories related to the multiverse
find aliens etc
why do countries invest so much money
into space exploration what's the end
goal since we are a future human would
never be able to travel faster than
light and reach these places in our
lifetimes
okay the james webb space telescope
multiverse no
we cannot see what is beyond our
universe we don't even know how big our
universe is we can only see a small
portion
of the universe
the actual universe is way bigger than
what we can see the observable universe
is about about roughly 90
billion light years in diameter roughly
give or take
right beyond that we don't know what
there is so we can't even see
our own universe in its entirety so how
will we know what's beyond our universe
so we can never
so the multiverse theory is not really
scientific it's just philosophy it's
just ideology
it is not a falsifiable theory and
that's why it's not a scientific theory
so the james webb telescope will show us
nothing about the multiverse aliens
possibly
so this telescope could possibly detect
signatures of life in the atmospheres of
exoplanets which are planets planets
that uh
surround that that are in orbit around
other stars
so possibly from that perspective we may
detect indirect evidence of aliens
possibly
um
and the groundbreaking discoveries it's
going to make are that it's going to be
it's going to allow us to peer way back
into the into the past of into the past
history of the universe so it it is
going to observe the universe in the
infrared wavelength which means that it
is going to
be able to detect galaxies essentially
the first galaxies that ever formed in
our universe's history so that's going
to show us a lot about
that we don't know about right so that
in brief is what it's going to do we are
going to be observing the universe in a
totally different wavelength which is
going to open up a whole different
dimension of the universe to us
and that's going to happen
very soon it's summer time now it's all
it's almost summer so maybe in a couple
of months we may have the first proper
observations from this telescope which
is going to
i believe totally revolutionize
observational astronomy and the
understanding of the universe as we have
it right so that's what this telescope
is going to do
one very much hopes so
now why do countries invest so much into
space exploration because
all of the technologies that go into
creating
these instruments these rockets these
spacecraft these technologies
also have other applications
they eventually make their way into the
civilian domain but they also have
military applications
and
they have all these spin-offs right so
any new technology you develop let's say
for space it's going to have a multi
multitude of applications in other
domains it's going to make you more
technologically advanced and that is
always good for any country
the greatest civilizations are the ones
throughout history that have been the
most technologically advanced
and that is one of the lessons of
history we learn from indian
civilization itself india was for most
of its time period from for most of its
history the most technologically
advanced civilization in the world and
that's why it was the greatest economy
so this is all
uh interrelated so if you develop new
technologies groundbreaking technologies
whether it's in space exploration or
whatever it helps you technologically
and it
and if the americans are doing it it
means they want to retain their
technologically their technological
superiority and primacy in the world
so that's why they are investing heavily
in this and also
nowadays space has a geopolitical
dimension
very soon the americans and the chinese
are going to send humans to the moon
eventually they're going to stake claim
to
parts of the moon they're going to say
it's part of our
it's our territory now the same will
happen with mars eventually so india
also has to ensure it doesn't get left
behind in all of these things so
space
technology has multiple uses including
military uses which is very important
for countries
and also space has a geopolitical
dimension
uh
future nuclear reactors could use
helium-3 from the moon which is found in
great abundance in the lunar soil so
these are reasons why
countries are investing so much in space
exploration nowadays even private
companies like spacex blue origin and so
on
so that is the end goal
it's not a long term end goal it's a
more immediate objective
to retain our technological to for each
country to retain to advance its
technology
to achieve technological primacy in the
in the global pecking order
and to maybe in the future
acquire territory beyond the earth
which you can then exploit for various
purposes so these are the reasons why
countries invest so much into space
exploration and that's why india also
needs to ensure it doesn't get left
behind
kevin kevin says kevin chenowe says the
universe expands faster than the speed
of light it's continuously accelerating
if a particular particle is traveling at
the speed of the expansion of the
universe isn't it tending to be to
become non-existent as far as our
universe is concerned
as in the speed at the speed of light
due to time dilation time freezes the
particle is going in the past well
experientially maybe
not as per its path movement and
therefore towards the creation of the
universe therefore approaching that
non-existent state
so does the expansion of the universe
result in its inevitable annihilation
okay let's understand what the
super luminal expansion of the universe
means
when you say that the particle that a
particle is traveling at the speed of
the expansion of the universe
it doesn't mean it's traveling through
space-time
it means space-time itself is expanding
imagine you have a birthday balloon
you blow it up it becomes bigger right
so let's say you have an ant sitting on
a balloon which is of this size and
you're blowing the balloon the balloon
gets bigger and bigger and bigger so
without moving the ant which is sitting
on the surface is getting further and
further away from any point on the
balloon
right so as the balloon expands
without traveling on the balloon without
walking on the balloon just by sitting
there the ant is getting further and
further away further and further away
because of the expansion of the balloon
the expansion of the universe is
something similar to that
it's an accelerating expansion space
time itself is expanding so a particle
is not traveling through space-time it
is just sitting in place but the space
time itself is going further away and
the further you are from here
the further the the acceleration is
and the faster that particle is getting
away from from us and there comes a
point where the expansion of the
universe is super luminal
from our perspective which means that
it's expanding faster than the speed of
light
which doesn't break the rules of general
relativity it's because it is not
something that is traveling through
space time faster than the speed of
light it means the space time itself is
expanding faster than the speed of light
which is something that we experienced
during the
phenomenon of inflation in the very
early universe
in which the universe expanded super
luminally faster than the speed of light
and it's still happening right now
as we go further away
so what that does
is that every second that we exist
there are parts of the of the universe
that are going beyond our observable
horizon
which means
that the observable universe every
single second is getting smaller because
there are parts of the universe that are
now expanding
beginning to expand
faster than the speed of light which
means we can never see them again
they're going beyond our observable
limits
and eventually
after several
billion years
all we will be able to see
because of the
acceleration
accelerating expansion of the universe
eventually all we will be able to see is
just our local galaxy by the time our
galaxy will have merged with the
andromeda galaxy
so if humans still exist at the point
the only thing they will know about the
universe is the local galaxy nothing
else
because everything else would have
expanded away
with the expansion of the universe so
that is what we mean by the universe
becoming the observable universe
becoming smaller
it's because it's expanding so fast so
particles
become non-existent from our perspective
because they go beyond our observable
horizon
so they don't go back in time time
doesn't freeze time dilation happens
only when you're traveling inside space
time
time dilation doesn't apply when when
the space time itself expands and goes
further away
so that's something you will understand
if you actually study
let's say special relativity or general
relativity but that's what i can say in
in brief
okay sandeep says my question is about
the geopolitics around the north pole
according to many analysts the polar
regions will become more accessible
and hence more strategic in the future
because of climate change russia us
canada and scandinavia nations have an
advantage because they have a presence
there do you think tropical nations
like india will miss out on this or is
the whole
polar geopolitical angle overrated good
question very good question let's go
back to the
map where's the map okay let's go back
and take a look at the polar regions
so
the north pole is somewhere here
it shows me a flat representation so the
north pole if you can see my mouse
pointer is somewhere here
and as the earth's climate gets warmer
the polar regions which have throughout
most of recent history being covered in
ice will become more open you you will
see navigation becoming possible in
these regions
and many nations will start taking
advantage of that i'm sure there are
lots of
mineral resources and other resources
available there which are currently
locked up inside the ice that may be
freed up
so russia has a prime position there so
does
canada so does the us
and so do certain scandinavian countries
because they have this
geographical proximity to the north pole
region
the chinese
they call themselves a near arctic
country
and they currently have a good
relationship with the russians which
means they
might get access through russia to the
polar regions the chinese are already
calling it the polar silk road they will
send ships and ice breakers through this
region to
to engage in trade and transportation
and things like that
and they may also be allowed by the
russians to maybe engage in grilling
offshore work and things like that if
the things work out fine so the chinese
may have access to the polar regions
through russia now india as you as you
rightly say is a po is an is a tropical
country it's far away from the polar
regions from the north pole so what does
india do
well let's take a bigger picture look at
geography let's go straight south of
india what do we find
we find antarctica we have unimpeded
access to antarctica nothing stands in
our way
if you stand at the beach
in somnath
and you look south
and you go south
you will have a direct access to
antarctica
if you if you take a ship and go south
you will reach antarctica without
anything coming in the way so india can
access antarctica it is hard for india
to access the north pole region but the
south pole region is
much more accessible from india's
perspective of course right now there is
this moratorium on exploiting antarctica
antarctica is the only unspoiled
continent as of today
the untouched continent no
exploitation of its resources is
currently allowed many countries
including india have scientific research
stations in antarctica
and maybe in the future
as the geopolitical situation changes as
the world order changes even antarctica
unfortunately may become open to
uh commercial exploitation in which case
it will be
not very difficult for india
to get involved in that
from the north pole perspective it's
difficult because of the geographical
situation but from the south pole
perspective it's much easier for india
so that's
the current situation
sparsh says in yesterday's episode you
showed a map of u.s bases in germany i
noticed that most of the bases were in
west germany and almost none in the east
why is it that even after the fall of
the berlin wall and the reunification of
germany the us did not open any new
bases in the eastern part does the u.s
not feel the need to open more bases in
the country
and the related question recently
germany allows announced that it will
invest
about 150 billion dollars in defense
what are the potential implications of
its this increase in the budget
and how does it impact germany nato
germany us and germany russia relations
the first question is about the u.s
bases in germany uh most of the us bases
are in east are in west germany uh the
reunification happened in the early 90s
1991 there abouts
and there was a long period of
reintegration because the
the lifestyle the the living standards
the economy of east germa germany was
terrible it was way lower than the rest
of germany
and uh for for the longest time i think
the people of west germany had to pay an
additional tax just to support the
rebuilding of east germany i believe it
may still be in place right now if i'm
not mistaken
so uh
so that's how it was now all of the
american military bases where in west
germany i think that there was no real
need or reason for the americans to open
bases in east germany because the whole
of the country was now under
nato control
so they had control anyway
and the purpose of these bases
was to uh
essentially target the ussr
the the purpose of nato was to encircle
the ussr to counter balance the ussr and
now that the ussr was gone russia was in
place at that time russia was very weak
very weak broken economy they broke the
economy further using the the proxy of
boris yeltsin
so i think there was no real need for
the americans to put bases in east
germany it's just a few hundred
kilometers here and there
and the real purpose of the bases was to
have planes and missiles
in place that could target
russia
on demand
so that's a purpose they are already
able to serve
with the bases that they have in west
germany so i think it was just not
necessary it was not needed it did not
serve any real purpose that's what i
imagine it would be
now the second question is about the
increase in the german defense budget
about 150 billion dollars
the potential implications this the
straightforward implications is that
it's going to boost the american economy
because all of this hardware military
hardware will be bought from the us
so it's great for the u.s economy it's
great for the u.s military industrial
complex
they will
be able to boost
production manufacturing maybe add a few
jobs to their economy good for the u.s
so how does it impact germany nato it
will make nato stronger it will
it will bolster the us economy and make
nato stronger so it's win-win for the us
it's good for germany as well because
russia is now
more
assertive more proactive
so that's how it is and how will it
affect germany russia relations their
relations will remain more or less the
same
the relations
aren't terribly bad
i mean the germans are buying large
quantities of
russian gas the whole of europe is doing
that that will continue
of course with the new hardware the
germans see the germans don't really
control their military germany is a
country that's under u.s military
occupation everything is under de facto
control of the us
so uh it's going to give the us a little
bit more hardware to play with
in
in the nato regions and that may not be
a very good thing for russia in the long
run the russians may also ramp up
defense production and maybe increase if
they can
if they can afford to the size of their
military strength
so essentially it's it's a good thing
for the u.s that's what i can say
richard says there's a famous line that
time is meaningless in quantum mechanics
what does it mean and how
is it
possible
time is meaningless in quantum mechanics
what does it mean so the thing is this
see in quantum mechanics time is
understood to be an external concept a
classical concept
it is external to the system under
consideration let's say we are talking
about the evolution of an electron
so we are considering the evolution of
the electron in time the electron has a
wave function and so on and we have the
schrodinger equation which which governs
it there is a time dependence linear
equation and so on so forth
so time is a consideration in quantum
mechanics but it is an external factor
it's a classical concept it does not
emerge out of the theory of quantum
mechanics itself it is external to the
theory
it is something that is taken as
something that already exists
now in general relativity for instance
you have the situation that space time
tells matter
how to move
and the matter tells space time how to
curve which means that in general
relativity space time is dynamic gravity
is a manifestation of the geometry of
space time which is why general
relativity is also called geometric
dynamics
but no such thing exists in quantum
mechanics there is no relationship
apart from this external relationship
between time and the system under under
consideration
uh so we don't know what quite what time
is it doesn't emerge out of quantum
mechanics
right now there is this
research that
indicates that possibly time could be
an entanglement phenomenon something
that emerges out of quantum entanglement
so that is still something that's
ongoing we still don't quite know
time is still a concept that is not very
well understood we don't quite know what
time is time is very mysterious in
physics in the whole of physics we don't
know what time is where does time come
from is it an emerging phenomenon is it
something that is external to all
systems
are there atoms and molecules of time
we don't know any of that so time
as of today
is
external in quantum mechanics which
means that's why some people would say
that it is meaningless
in quantum mechanics
yeshua then says
is it possible to understand vedas after
graduation is it crucial to no sanskrit
in order to understand the vedas and
other indian teachings
is it too late for people on above 20
to relearn ancient indian philosophies
and knowledge
it is possible to understand the vedas
anytime in life
even before graduation even after
graduation you have to put in the time
to study study the texts
is it crucial to know sanskrit to
understand the vedas and indian
teachings it helps a lot
if you don't know sanskrit then you have
to rely on translations either into
indian languages or in english
if there is if you are relying on a
translation in an indian language let's
say hindi or bengali or whatever
language you prefer or kannada or tamil
whichever language you prefer
then
what we find is that translations from
sanskrit to indian languages
are quite accurate
but translations from sanskrit to
english
are often very unreliable
because they are typically done by
western professors
and
those cannot be trusted unfortunately
there have been many
many instances many cases of deliberate
distortions and mistranslations
there is this very infamous example
of the translation of the bodhiana sutra
by
by by romulan
in which an
in which a westward migration of indians
was distorted and misinterpreted as an
eastward migration of indians that's
what ramallah tapa did and this was
comprehensively debunked
right so this was a translation from
sanskrit
to english so this is just one example
lots of such examples exist and
therefore it is
i would say it is important to
to read to study the vedas other
teachings in either an indian language
a modern indian language
tamil telugu kannada gujarati
marathi hindi
whatever
or
in sanskrit itself if you can so that is
the right way to learn it indian english
translations are not typically reliable
i if you want to study the bhagavad gita
i would highly recommend the english
translation of the big debra
which i think is the best translation
i've come across there are many english
versions of the rig of the bhagavad-gita
i don't recommend any of those except
the translation by bibek devroy it's a
straight translation there is no mumbo
jumbo in it there is no interpretation
it is a straight translation that's what
you should study so that is one english
translation that i would recommend i
would not recommend any other english
translations and the third question is
is it too late for people about 20 to
relearn ancient indian philosophies and
knowledge no it's not too late you can
certainly begin after 20 why not
so do that all the best
ganpat vaguela says many sri lankans are
coming to india because of the current
economic situation in the country my
question is how will it affect india
economically and socially
socially there's not
so how will it affect india as long as
the influx of refugees is small
it's not a problem india can absorb a
few dozen refugees maybe a couple of
hundred refugees or something like that
maybe even a few thousand refugees but
if it becomes large numbers like
thousands of people coming in that
becomes a problem for the local economy
because who's going to
feed these people who's going they will
need accommodation they will need to be
fed
temporarily however long they stay in
india and so on so that's going to be a
burden a stress on the indian economy it
can be handled for a certain period of
time but if it becomes a long-term
phenomenon
then it becomes a problem it becomes a
strain on the indian economy we are not
a dharamshala
actually
we are that's what we've been turning to
anyway that's a different story
so
if there are too many refugees coming in
then it could become a problem
it could become
a strain on the local economy they would
come into tamil nadu whereas will they
go because that's
that's the geographical region where
that abuts sri lanka let's look at the
map in case you are not aware
the place they would come to the closest
place to sri lanka is the rameshwaram
which is parts of tamil nadu right
so that's what the weather would come so
it would become a stress
a stress stressor on the local economy
and if there is economic stress there is
social stress also so that's the only
thing apart from that the cultural
factor is not an issue the culture is
the same whether it is a similar
scenario culture or tamil culture
culturally is the same and mostly i
imagine it would it would be people from
northern sri lanka which means that
tamil people would come in
so what needs to be what needs to be
done is that
india needs to happen that the situation
in sri lanka doesn't go out of control i
think it's going to be up to india to
kind of
rebalance
and stabilize sri lanka to some extent
and it's going to be best for india and
for sri lanka as well if india
intervenes and doesn't let china or some
other country intervene because then the
sri lankans will have to pay a big a
heavy price for whatever
for whatever aid they get
right so
that's what i can say so i hope this
refugee thing does it doesn't become a
big
big factor
and i hope that the situation is brought
back under control
soon
pranav says what should we do as youth
of india to make this country a world
superpower again
you cannot do anything directly but what
you can do
is
to make india superpower every person
what they can do is
reach your
fullest potential
right that's what you should do
if you have a country of people young
people who have reached only half of
their potential that's going to be a
mediocre country
if you have a country of young people
who are not ambitious
who are mediocre then the country is
going to wallow in mediocrity but if you
have a country of young dynamic people
who reach their full potential
who maximize their potential in which
whatever field they are
then you will have a country that is
progressing rapidly
in a country with a great future
so you have to
first of all determine whatever your
best at what is your aptitude what is
what is your the thing that you're
really good at so not everybody can be a
scientist not everybody can be a
business person not everybody can be an
entrepreneur not everybody can be a
programmer not everybody can be an
artist
but everybody has something that they're
good at
so find whatever it is that you're good
at and do your best to excel at that
and achieve your fullest potential
as a professional as a creative person
as whatever you are and also
economically and financially because if
you become prosperous you can create
more jobs and you can make the country
more prosperous so that in short is what
the youth of india should do to make
india eventually a superpower again
all right my friends there are so many
more questions but i think i'm at the
end of today's session it's almost two
hours so thank you very much for all the
questions thank you for your viewership
i really appreciate it thank you for all
your support in whatever way it is
i really appreciate it
and i will see you in next week's
episodes until then
take care
have a good day have a good night thank
you bye